Stenzor, Isidor. Collection. 6036/020
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Stenzor, Isidor. Collection
1922-1977
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Stenzor, Isidor
6036/020
0.33 cubic feet
0.333333333333333 linear ft.
Articles, reprints, pamphlets, correspondence, photographs.
This collection includes correspondence, an autobiographical sketch, and files on the Communist Party and the Communist Party of the USA.
5767596
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff, September 07, 2011
EAD encoding:
Kathryn Dowgiewicz, January 10, 2013
Biographical / Historical
Founded in 1900 by local union delegates representing about 2,000 members in cities in the northeastern United States, the ILGWU grew in geographical scope, membership size, political influence to become one of the most powerful forces in American organized labor by mid-century. Representing workers in the women's garment industry, the ILGWU worked to improve working and living conditions of its members through collective bargaining agreements, training programs, health care facilities, cooperative housing, educational opportunities, and other efforts. In 1995, the ILGWU merged with the Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union (ACTWU) to form the Union of Needletrades, Industrial and Textile Employees (UNITE).
Biographical / Historical
Isidor Stenzor (spelling variations include Isidore and Steinzor) was born on March 3, 1893 in Kassov, Poland, and arrived in the United States in October of 1909. Soon after, he found work in a men's clothing factory as an operator, enduring long hours, low wages, and horrible conditions. After initially becoming involved in various garment operator unions and locals from the United Garment Workers to the Amalgamated Clothing Workers, in 1915, Stenzor joined the ILGWU and New York Cloak Operators Local 1. He held numerous union positions in New York, including an Executive Board member of Local 1, Chairman of the Cloak and Dress Joint Board, and Manager of the Price Adjustment Department of the New York Cloak Joint Board. He then moved to Canada to become the Manager of the Montreal Cloak Joint Board from 1939-1943. In 1950, Stenzor was appointed the Manager of the Los Angeles Cloak Joint Board, a position he held until his retirement.
Stenzor was active in many organizations, including Chairman of the Jewish Labor Committee for the Pacific Coast Region and active in the Workmen's Circle and Jewish Socialist Federation. Stenzor died on March 27, 1988 at the age of 95.
Scope and Contents
The collection of Isidor Stenzor covers the years between 1920 through the 1970s providing information on both his professional activity for the ILGWU as well as his personal activities and engagements. A large portion of the collection is in Yiddish. There is general union correspondence, reports and statements for various committees and Joint Boards of which Stenzor was involved. Also included are clippings, articles and statements regarding the centralization of control in the garment industry. The Uniform Industrial Control Plan aimed at allowing one business agent to gain control over a manufacturer as well as the inside shop and contractors. According to the plan and the included report, the business agent would have complete supervision by holding meetings, listening to complaints, and settling prices.
Additionally, a significant amount of the collection contains material collected during Stenzor's time as a communist. From the Communist Party and Communist Party of the USA, there are mailings, letters, statements, information from meetings, doctrines, bulletins, and expulsion of members. Much of the correspondence involves Jay Lovestone and Charles Zimmerman. There are requests for Stenzor to appear before the party in regards to the merger of the Cloakmakers Progressive League with the Trade Union Center and other involvements with Cloakmakers Local 1. Also included is material from the Council of Needle Trades Progressive Groups and the Independent Labor League of America (a Constitution and a Discussion Bulletin). The collection contains material regarding anti-war activities, including information, correspondence, flyers and meeting minutes for the group "Keep America Out of War," in which Stenzor was a member of the New York Council before resigning.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: 5780: ILGWU records 5780/014: ILGWU. Local 22. Charles Zimmerman papers 5780/046: ILGWU. Los Angeles Joint Board records 6036/028: Lovestone, Jay.
Stenzor, Isidor.; International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union -- Archives.
5767596
- General correspondence, 1920-1936 (Box 1, Folder 1a)
  Scope and Contents
  Includes case against Elias Marks (indicted for criminal anarchy), 1920; letters to Morris Sigman appealing GEB decision removing him as local 1 officer, 1924; report on the general strike in the cloak industry of New York, submitted by the minority of the GEB, 1926.
- General correspondence, 1951-1969 (Box 1, Folder 1b)
- Autobiographical sketch, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  In Yiddish.
- Communist Party and Communist Party of the USA (Majority Group, also known as opposition or Lovestone group) [folder 1 of 2], 1922- 1929 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Communist Party and Communist Party of the USA (Majority Group, also known as opposition or Lovestone group) [folder 2 of 2], 1922- 1930 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Communist Party and Communist Party (Majority Group), 1930-1933 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Communist Party and Communist Party (Majority Group), 1934-1939 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Erlich-Alter 25th Anniversary Memorial, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Keep America Out of War Committee (aka Congress) and other anti-war groups, 1938-1940 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  Includes correspondence with Jay Lovestone and Stenzor letter explaining his resignation from committee, 1940.
- Local 1 and 17 controversy, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Los Angeles Bund, Workmens Circle and Socialist Farband, 1955-1966 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Uniform Industrial Control Plan (centralization), 1938-1939 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  Plan to give one business agent control over a given jobber and all his production.